In this video, we will be looking at the
basics
of electrostatics. First of all, what is
electrostatics?
Electrostatics is the study of physics
which
deals with forces based off charge.
Now, what is charge? Electric charge is a
property
of matter that causes electrical forces.
and electrical interactions. And there are
two
types of charges. The first type is
positive
charge, the second type is negative.
And there's a good chance that you've
already
learned this, but like charges repel, and
opposite
charges attract.
So like charges repel, while opposite
charges repel. Attract.
If you don't know what this means, well,
if
you have a positively charged object,
let's
say a positively charged particle, going
close
to another positively charged object,
there
is going to be a force that makes them go
away
from each other. We'll learn more about
that
in the upcoming videos about Coulomb's
law.
And same thing goes with a negative
charge,
close with a negative charge, they repel.
However, if you have a positive charge
with
a negative charge, there is going to be a
force
that brings them together, because
opposite
charges attract. The unit for charge is a
coulomb,
c. And this is how we basically measure
the
magnitude of charge. Now, how do charges
work?
Well, we're going to go into a bit of the
atomic
view. And this sort of relates to
chemistry
as well. Atoms contain protons, which are
positively
charged particles, and
electrons. And
in most situations, electrons are the only
charges
that move easily, because they're in
orbit,
or they're found around the electron.
And we have a key principle that we can
use.
And this is called the conservation of
charge.
And this basically states that the total
charge
in a system can't be destroyed or created.
It's just transferred from an object to
another.
This means that neutral charges, which
are charges with a net charge of zero,
will
be accepting or releasing electrons.
Depends on what the charged object is.
And there are three types of ways where an
object
can get charged. First of all, there is
charging,
charging by friction.
So that's when you rub two objects
together.
And when two different materials are
rubbed,
electrons can transfer due to different
attractions
of electrons. So for example, if you have
rubber
and fabric, one object gains electrons and
becomes
negatively charged, while the other loses
electrons
and becomes positively charged. And there
is
going to be a chart that says which
material
is more likely to gain or lose electrons.
But this is mostly grade 9 and grade 10
science.
So it might come up, but all you have to
do
is really know the types of charges.
The second one is charging by contact.
Charging by conduction.
That's what it's called. And that's when a
charged
object, so plus or minus, it has to be
charged,
touches a neutral object, and the charge
basically
redistributes until both charges are the
same.
It's kind of like the same concept as
heat.
If you've done thermal physics or thermal
chemistry
before, they're going to end up, for
example,
when a hot object touches a cold object,
they're
going to end up at the same temperature in
the
middle. And it's the same thing for
charge.
So if we have a net positive charge here
and
a neutral charge here, let's say this one
has
a charge of like 10 coulombs, then at the
end,
both objects are going to end up with 5
coulombs
of charge. Charging by induction is more,
it's more, there are more steps to it.
And you have probably learned this before,
induction.
It's when a charged object is brought near
a
non-charged object. So let's say we have a
non-charged
object over here, and then we bring a
charged
object, let's say a positive rod, towards
and
really close to the charged object. So
basically,
all the electrons or all the negative
charges
are going to be attracted to the positive
charges.
And since all the negative charges are
attracted
to the positive charges, basically this
object
behaves as a temporary positive charge.
Think of it as sort of a temporary dipole.
And the ground only sees this positive
charge.
So when you ground this object, for
example,
when you touch it, there is going to be
more
electrons going in because it's going to
see
that it's a positive charge, or the thing
it
sees is a positive charge. So when you
ground
it, for example, you touch it, there are
going
to be more electrons that come in and
balance
this out, but there are still these
electrons
here. So now, overall, when you remove
these
two, there is going to be an overall
negative
charge. And these are the types of
chargeings.
Now, let's talk about conductors and
insulators
now. So conductors are materials where
electrons
can move easily or freely. So things like
metals.
Metals are really good conductors. If you
do
chemistry, you know that it's because
there's
a lattice of electrons. And basically,
extra charge spreads out over the surface
that
is mobile. Also, ionic substances that are
dissolved
into ions, those are also good conductors.
For example, if you put salt in water.
That's
why you should never put electronics in
water
because although pure water is not
conductive,
it's almost never pure. There's some sort
of
metal or ion, for example, there are bits
zinc in water or other metals, so that's
why
water should not be near electronics.
Insulators are basically the polar
opposite
of conductors. And these are materials
where
the electrons are really, really tightly
bound.
For example, rubber is a really, really
good
insulator. It's a very common one as well.
Glass and dry wood.
And these are basically two types of
different
materials that either conduct or not
conduct
electricity. And that's basically it for
the
introduction of electrostatics.
Basically, I feel like the most important
thing
you need to know is this part where our
charges
repel and opposite charges attract. These
are
all mostly review. You should be able to
be
familiarized with these, but it's not
gonna
come up in your test that much.
But it's still good to know. Thank you
guys
for watching, and next video we'll be
exploring
forces of charges in Coulomb's Law. Thank
you!